Guide to the Fred E. Pond Papers Related to Fishing
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Fred E. Pond papers related to fishing
1750-1947
1876-1922
GEN MSS 904
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.33
(4 boxes)
The papers contain correspondence, photographs, drawings, writings, and ephemera primarily related to fishing, publications on fishing, and the history of fishing. Much of the correspondence is in regard to the life and work of the author Henry William Herbert ("Frank Forester") and includes letters from his daughter Margaret Herbert Mather and various authors, booksellers, and independent researchers. The papers also hold correspondence and material on three other writers of interest to Pond: Kit Clarke, Charles Hallock and Isaac McLellan. Also present are more than fifty photographic portraits of notable men active in field sports and sporting publications, ephemeral items such as cigarette and trade cards bearing images of fish and fishing, a book of sketches of fishermen by Wakeman Holberton, a watercolor by Joseph F. Sabin inscribed to collector David Wagstaff, and a group of letters and manuscripts related to the sport of fishing.
Pond, Fred. E. (Frederick Eugene), 1856-1925
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lindley Eberstadt, 1975.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Fred E. Pond (1856-1925)
The American sporting editor and bibliographer Frederick Eugene Pond, also known as "Will Wildwood," was born in Packwaukee, Marquette County, Wisconsin, on April 8, 1856, one of four children born to Simeon and Flora Hotchkiss Pond. Especially interested in the history of field sports in America and in the bibliography of sporting publications, Pond's particular focus was the work of Henry William Herbert (1807-1858), a British-born author who wrote under the name "Frank Forester" and was the most prominent sporting writer in nineteenth-century America.
Pond moved to New York in 1881 to become the field editor of Turf, Field, and Farm, after which he returned to Wisconsin to publish and edit Wildwood's Magazine from 1888 until it merged with Turf, Field, and Farm in 1889. He served as editor of Sportsmen's Review (Cincinnati) from 1897 to 1917 and of American Angler (New York) from 1917 to 1918, and wrote the "rod and gun" column in the New York Herald-Herald Tribune from 1923 to his death. Works of other authors edited by Pond include two volumes of writings by Henry William Herbert in 1879 and 1881, Isaac McLellan's Poems of the Rod and Gun (1886), and Charles Hallock's An Angler's Reminiscences (1913). Among Pond's own writings were Hand-book for Young Sportsmen (1876), Memoirs of Eminent Sportsmen (1878), Gun Trial and Field Records of America (1883), The Sportsman's Directory (1891), and Fishcraft, a Treatise on Fresh Water Fish and Fishing (1922); his Life and Adventures of "Ned Buntline" was first serialized in Wildwood's Magazine and later released in a limited edition volume (1919). Pond died in New York on November 1, 1925, and was buried in Warwick, New York, near a memorial erected to the memory of Henry William Herbert.
Scope and Contents
The papers contain correspondence, photographs, drawings, writings, and ephemera primarily related to fishing, publications on fishing, and the history of fishing. Much of the correspondence is in regard to the life and work of the author Henry William Herbert ("Frank Forester") and includes letters from his daughter Margaret Herbert Mather, various authors, booksellers, and independent researchers, and floor plans of his home in Newark, New Jersey. The papers also hold correspondence and material on three other writers of interest to Pond: Kit Clarke, Charles Hallock and Isaac McLellan. Also present are more than fifty photographic portraits of notable men active in field sports and sporting publications, ephemeral items such as cigarette and trade cards bearing images of fish and fishing, and a group of letters and manuscripts related to the sport.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Correspondence and Writings, 1876-1922. II. Papers Related to Authors, 1863-1918. III. Visual Materials, 1875-1930. IV. Other Papers, 1750-1947.
Fishers -- United States; Fishing -- United States; Cabinet photographs -- United States -- 19th century; Cartes-de-visite (card photographs) -- United States -- 19th century; Cigarette cards -- United States -- 19th century; Drawings (visual works) -- United States -- 19th century; Photographs -- United States -- 19th century; Tintypes (prints) -- United States -- 19th century; Trade cards (advertising) -- United States -- 19th century; Watercolors (paintings) -- United States -- 19th century; Fishers -- United States; Clarke, Kit; Durivage, Francis A. (Francis Alexander), 1814-1881; Faddis, W. I.; Forester, Frank, 1807-1858; Grinnell, George Bird, 1849-1938; Hallock, Charles, 1834-1917; Herbert, Henry William, 1807-1858; Holberton, Wakeman; Hornby, E. B. (Eliza Benedict), 1835-1917; Mather, Margaret Herbert; McLellan, Isaac, 1806-1899; Oakes, James, 1807-1878; Picton, Thomas, 1822-1891; Pond, Fred. E. (Frederick Eugene), 1856-1925; Raymond, George B.; Sabin, J. F. (Joseph F.), 1846-1926; Sibley, Henry Hastings, 1811-1891; Thorpe, Thomas Bangs, 1815-1878; Warren, T. Robinson (Thomas Robinson), 1828-1915; Zimmerman, Charles A., 1844-1909; Sabin, J. F. (Joseph F.), 1846-1926 -- Presentation inscription to D Wagstaff; Wagstaff, David, 1882-1951 -- Presentation inscription from J. F. Sabin
- Correspondence and Writings, 1876-1922; Series I; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into two subseries: Correspondence, and Writings.
  Scope and Contents
  The series primarily contains letters related to Pond's interest in the author Henry William Herbert ("Frank Forester"), including correspondence with his daughter Margaret Herbert Mather, and various authors, booksellers, and independent researchers. Pond was in touch with the most active collectors of Frank Forester; their correspondence sheds much light on the author's career and contains information of bibliographical importance. Literary pseudonyms of correspondents follow their names.
  - Correspondence
    - Burrell, Mary H., 1913-1919 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      General note
      Mrs. Burrell was an historian and genealogist, as well as an editor, who assisted Pond in his research into the life and works of Henry William Herbert; many of her lengthy letters concern Newark, New Jersey, where Herbert lived, and describe the results of her inquiries.
    - Durivage, Francis A. (Francis Alexander), 1877-1880 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Includes an autograph manuscript autobiographical sketch and an autograph manuscript biographical sketch of Boston merchant and sporting writer James Oakes ("Acorn") probably written by Durivage for the periodical Spirit of the Times. Durivage was an well-known author and journalist who contributed to several of the publications edited by Pond.
    - Eaton, George Boardman ("Jacobstaff"), 1906 Mar 10 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Faddis, W. I. ("Toxophilius"), 1876-1877 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Correspondence relating to Faddis's interest in Henry William Herbert, his life and works, and other American sporting writers.
    - Hornby, E. B. (Eliza Benedict), 1913-1914 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Mather, Margaret Herbert, 1886-1899 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Seventeen letters, many of considerable length, discussing the biography of her father, Henry William Herbert, his books, etc. Mrs. Mather edited The Poems of Frank Forester just at the time of this correspondence, and the letters are full of information and reflections on this editorial work.
    - McLellan, Isaac, 1898 Oct 18 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Picton, Thomas ("Paul Preston"), 1876 July 5 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Picton was an important journalist and sporting writer of the time.
    - Raymond, George B., 1876-1915 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Correspondence relating to the collecting of sporting books, especially the works of Henry William Herbert, containing many notes on bibliographical problems, rarity, etc.
    - Sibley, Henry Hastings ("Hal a Dacotah"), 1876-1888 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Includes a cabinet portrait photograph of Sibley by C. A. Zimmerman and inscribed to Pond, a clipped article by Sibley, and a published biographical sketch of Sibley.
    - Thorpe, Henry, 1879-1880 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Thorpe was a New York book dealer.
    - Thorpe, Thomas Bangs, 1877-1878 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Warren, T. Robinson (Thomas Robinson), 1876-1894 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Includes an autograph manuscript autobiographical essay; Warren was a pupil of Henry William Herbert and his reminiscences of that author are a major portion of his manuscript.
    - Zimmerman, Charles A., 1876-1880 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Zimmerman was a photographer in St. Paul, Minnesota, who photographed many sportsmen
    - General correspondence, 1876-1920 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Letters addressed to Pond, many in his capacity as editor of various sporting publications and mostly dealing with editorial questions, book collecting, Henry William Herbert/Frank Forester, bibliography, planned articles, sporting recollections, history of sport in America, etc.
  - Writings
    - "American Fish Culture, Its Origins and Utility", 1907 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Typescript, signed
    - Biographical material, 1922, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Contains clipped entries from Who's Who in America, and a manuscript biography titled "The Death of Mr. Fred E. Pond - Will Wildwood."
- Papers Related to Authors, 1863-1918; Series II; 0.21; (1 box)
  Series II is organized into four subseries: Kit Clarke, Charles Hallock, Henry William Herbert, and Isaac McLellan.
  The series contains correspondence, research material, and printed material related to four authors of interest to Pond.
  - Kit Clarke
    - Correspondence, 1884-1918 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      Includes one letter from Clarke to Pond (1918), and ten letters from others to Clarke.
    - Illustrations, 1884, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
      Contains one graphite drawing of a trout, two ink sketches of outdoorsmen, and one engraving of a fish.
    - Other papers, 1888-1906 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      Contains copyright paperwork, notes, and ephemera advertising Clarke's publications and endorsements.
  - Charles Hallock
    - Correspondence with Fred Pond, 1876-1917, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Letters from others to Hallock, 1875-1910 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      Includes correspondence with George Bird Grinnell.
    - "Hallock's Poems", 1854-1904 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      Notebook containing autograph manuscript poems and printed poems clipped from periodicals.
    - Portrait photographs, 1906, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Writings, 1863-1912 (Box 2, Folder 25-26)
      Primarily articles and essays clipped from periodicals; includes an issue of the Hamilton, Bermuda, Royal Gazette 36, no. 38, September 22, 1863, with Hallock's article on the Confederate states, and a printed copy of his Vacation Rambles in Northern Michigan (1878).
    - Other papers, 1906, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Henry William Herbert ("Frank Forester")
    - Bibliography, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
      Prepared by Pond; in addition to publications lists, includes sections on: buyers and admirers of Books by Forester; Herbert's friends; members of the Friends of Frank Forester group; and census of libraries owning books by Forester, with other notes.
    - Bibliographic material, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
      Includes a printed poem by Herbert, and copies of advertisements for the Pond's "Foresterian Library" collection.
    - Biographical material, 1888-1916, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
      Includes printed images of Henry William Herbert.
    - Article about Henry William Herbert's home and gravesite, tear sheet from New York Herald, 1893 Nov 26 (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 31)
    - Unidentified artist, floor plans of Herbert's home, "The Cedars," in Newark, New Jersey, undated (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 32-34)
      Measured drawings, graphite and ink on paper.
  - Isaac McLellan
    - "The Hunter, Angler & Tourist"; poem, autograph manuscript, signed, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Scrapbook, 1886-1899 (Box 2, Folder 36)
      Small commercial notebook (writing book) containing poems and reviews clipped from newspapers and serials, pasted and laid in. One clipped poem, laid in, has a small photographic portrait of McLellan affixed in the lower margin. Also present in folder: obituary for McLellan.
    - Tear sheets with McLellan's writings, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
      Six sheets removed from printed publications; includes poems and "Ontwa--an Indian Story."
- Visual Materials, 1875-1930; Series III; 0.42; (1 box)
  Series III is organized into three subseries: Drawings and Paintings, Ephemera, and Photographs.
  The series contains a variety of visual images related to fishing: advertising material, photographs, and artistic images of fishing. Prominent are more than fifty portraits of sportsmen and sporting publishers, including those related to the journal Turf, Field, and Farm.
  - Drawings and Paintings
    - Holberton, Wakeman, "Humourous Sketches", undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
      Sketchbook (disbound) with title page "Humourous Sketches," containing 21 ink and graphite sketches showing amusing scenes of the sporting life, mostly angling, each about 9 x 11 inches. Holberton (1839-1898) was a well-known sportsman who painted fish and game subjects.
    - Sabin, J. F. (Joseph F.), undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
      Watercolor on paper mounted on card, 4 x 5 inches; inscribed on verso in ink: Water color by me Jos F Sabin To Mr. David Wagstaff - Happy New Year.
  - Ephemera
    Items in this subseries bear images of or advertising for firms involved with angling.
    - Cigarette cards, circa 1900 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Postcards, undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Stationery, undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Trade cards, calendar, calling cards, and event tickets, circa 1875-1900 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Photographs
    Portraits in this subseries are of sportsmen involved with angling or shooting, or authors or artists who created images relating to field sports.
    - "Photos of Forester-Land", circa 1930 (Box 3, Folder 45)
      Scenery in and around Warwick, New York, and nearby Greenwood Lake.
    - Portraits - carte de visite and tintype formats, 1879-1890 (Box 3, Folder 46)
      Includes images of Nahum D. Ballou, Colin Campbell, Herman W. DeLong, Augustine Egbert, Charles E. Hoe, Charles F. Hotchkiss, R. Townsend Huddart, Fr. von Ivernois, H. A. Kanouse, L. J. Lee, Isaac McLellan, T. B. Reed, and W. F. Whitcher.
    - Portraits - cabinet card and other formats, 1877-1902 (Box 3, Folder 47)
      Contains images of Gustav Muss-Arnolt, Samuel T. Davis, W. C. Harris, James A. Henshall, Edward H. Hope, R. W. Hubbell, L. J. Lee, Frederick Freeman Lloyd, Thomas Ackley Logan, James Oakes, L. H. Smith, and John Henry Wallace.
    - Portraits, 1875-1901 (Box 3, Folder 48)
      Contains images of Spencer Fullerton Baird, Hamilton Busbey, William F. Carver, George Dawson, George Boardman Eaton, Charles E. Felton, Thomas T. Kinney, Marshall MacDonald, Charles E. Whitehead, John Sergeant Wise, and Thomas Whistler (of Newport, shown with the 60-pound bass he caught on September 8, 1875).
    - Portraits, Turf, Field, and Farm associates, circa 1880 (Box 3, Folder 49)
      A set of photographs mounted on similar bevel-cut boards, which had likely once been framed together; all men appear to have had a professional relationship with the journal Turf, Field, and Farm. Included are: Leslie C. Bruce, J. C. Corlies, A. J. Dunlap, Eugene Delmar, Malcolm W. Ford, George L. Frankenstein, Charles Pierre Goldey, George Herbert Henshaw, J. F. Johnson, H. W. Lacy, and R. G. Westmore.
    - Halftone portraits, undated (Box 3, Folder 50)
      Includes: Spencer F. Baird, A. Nelson Cheney, Theodatus Garlick, G. Brown Goode, Seth Green, James A. Henshall, Fred Mather, and Robert B. Roosevelt.
    - Portraits, unidentified, undated (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Stereographs, circa 1875 (Box 3, Folder 52)
      Three stereoviews of anglers.
- Other Papers, 1750-1947; Series IV; 11
  The series holds a variety of miscellaneous material on the topic of fishing, including letters, reference works, essays, and clippings. Also present are two eighteenth-century manuscripts related to fishing laws and the sea.
  - Pemberton Edgecomb, "An Act for the preservation of the fish called salmon, shad & alewives in the rivers, streams and waters within the counties of Lincoln and Cumberland...", 1799, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    Autograph manuscript, signed; published in part in the Massachusetts acts of January 1800. Accompanied by Lindley Eberstadt's research correspondence.
  - Joseph Green, "On Mr Boyles's singing an hymn of his own composing, at sea...", circa 1750 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    Manuscript, in an unknown hand, of a burlesque composed to parody Reverend Mather Byles.
  - Letter from Joseph Jefferson to William Winter, 1883 June 25 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - John O'Connor, "Index to plates in American Turf Register ", undated (Box 3, Folder 56)
    Typescript
  - Letters from William J. Porter to Col. H. S. Randall, 1866, undated (Box 3, Folder 57)
    Three letters: one autograph letter, signed, and two typescripts of other letters. Porter was founder and editor of Spirit of the Times, and editor of American Turf Register.
  - H. T. T, "A Veteran Angler's Fishing Memories", circa 1918 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    Autograph manuscript essay, author unknown.
  - Thomas Bangs Thorpe, "A Tradition of the Natchez", undated (Box 3, Folder 59)
    Typescript carbon transcript of a Thorpe story.
  - Miscellaneous ephemera, manuscripts, and other papers on angling and hunting, 1874, undated (Box 3, Folder 60)
    Includes Pond's childhood notebook "Complete List of Home and Foreign Sporting Journals," 1874
  - Miscellaneous poems clipped from newspapers, undated (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Miscellaneous general clippings, undated (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Tear sheets from Forest and Stream & Rod and Gun, 1882 (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 63)
    Containing reports on the fire at 37 Park Row.